There are lots of good reasons
to try and follow a healthier diet—
you lose weight,
you feel good,
but the main reason?
To live a longer, happier,
more productive life.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Did you know that taking human
growth hormone somatotropin
may actually accelerate
the aging process?
Here’s our first story.
Of all the anti-aging
clinic scams,
the selling and administration
of human growth hormone
has been called
"perhaps the most blatant
and organized form
of quackery today."
It all started,
promisingly enough,
with a small trial published
in the New England
Journal of Medicine
in which 12 men
over the age of 60
who got injections
of growth hormone
gained eight pounds of lean mass
over a period of six months,
compared to nine guys
who weren't injected.
Newspapers around the world
heralded the results,
anti-aging clinics popped up
to offer the injections
for $4,700 per month or more,
and the popular press
churned out books
extolling the hormone's
age reversing properties.
After all, that's how much
muscle mass one might lose
over 10 to 20 years of aging.
That's assuming, though,
that what they gained
was muscle.
The original study
didn't measure
muscle strength or performance,
but larger, longer, and better,
i.e. placebo-controlled studies,
subsequently did,
and found zero benefit.
A meta-analysis of studies
of growth hormone
for athletic performance
found that
it may even worsen
exercise capacity.
Wait, how can you gain
pounds of lean mass,
but not get any stronger?
By retaining pounds of water.
The lean mass was mostly
just due to fluid retention.
In fact, obvious swelling,
soft tissue edema,
is one of the most common
side effects of growth hormone,
affecting about
half of recipients.
Other side effects include
joint aches,
carpal tunnel syndrome,
male breast development,
elevated blood sugars,
and new-onset diabetes.
All this with no evidence
of anti-aging effects.
If anything,
growth hormone may actually
accelerate the aging process.
For example,
those with acromegaly,
a disease
of excess growth hormone,
suffer disproportionately
from muscle weakness,
as well as diabetes,
high blood pressure,
artery dysfunction,
and bone loss.
In the 1980s,
doctors and parents
conspired to inject short kids
with growth hormone
to try to make them grow taller.
What happened to them?
A study following
thousands of children
who were injected decades ago
with growth hormone,
for one reason or another,
found they had
a 33 percent increased risk
of being dead,
largely from brain bleeds
and tumors.
The strokes would make sense
from blood pressure elevation,
and the malignancies
from the growth hormone-
induced rise
of the cancer-promoting
growth hormone IGF-1.
20,000 to 30,000 people
in the U.S.
are estimated
to use growth hormone
in a vain attempt
to combat aging,
a practice referred to in
a leading endocrinology journal
as a "medical fraud
of unprecedented proportions."
Given the adverse effects,
maybe it's good
that all the tested samples
of human growth hormone,
also known as somatotropin,
sourced from online pharmacies
were found to have
a fraction
of the labelled amount,
presumably due to degradation
from improper storage,
and the majority of samples
confiscated in another study
were counterfeit
and contained none at all.
There's also
a proliferation of pills
and nasal
or sublingual spray forms
that makes no biological sense,
as the hormone
is too large a protein
to effectively cross membranes,
and if swallowed,
is simply destroyed
in the stomach.
Given the risk of cancer
and potential
for a shortened lifespan,
one prominent clinician remarked
that maybe growth hormone
is a "true anti-aging drug"
in that it may
prematurely stop you
from growing any older.
In our next story,
we look at how DHEA levels
naturally decline with age.
So, does replenishing youthful
levels have restorative effects?
Dehydroepiandrosterone, DHEA,
is the most abundant
steroid hormone
circulating in the blood,
or rather, prohormone.
It's produced largely
by the adrenal glands
and is then
converted locally in tissues
into androgens,
male sex hormones,
or estrogens,
female sex hormones.
DHEA production in the body
peaks between the ages
of 25 to 35,
and then gradually
starts to decline
about 2 percent every year.
By one's 80s, DHEA production
is down about 80 percent
from peak values
in early adulthood.
Cross-sectional studies
found a link
between low DHEA levels
and impaired sexual function,
less vitality,
depressed mood,
lower bone mineral density,
and compromised
cognitive performance
in terms of executive function,
concentration, and memory.
Combined with
interventional studies
done on rodents
showing a wide range
of beneficial effects,
DHEA was heralded
as an "anti-aging
superhormone panacea,"
even though
rodent adrenal glands
don't even produce the stuff.
But U.S. DHEA sales grew
to more than $50 million a year
on the premise that
replenishing youthful levels
might have restorative effects.
Given the Premarin debacle
with estrogen replacement,
showing that the reversing
of age-related hormonal decline
can sometimes
do more harm than good,
clinical trials
were desperately needed.
But because DHEA
can't be patented,
there's been
little research interest
among drug companies
to study it.
In fact,
part of its mass appeal is that,
due to a legal loophole,
DHEA is the only steroid
that's not considered
a controlled substance,
and therefore is available
over the counter
as a "dietary supplement,"
rather than
a prescription only drug.
Thankfully,
a series of long-term,
high-quality randomized
controlled trials
started to be published
within the last 20 years,
and early enthusiasm
was replaced
by a sober skepticism
as the "panacea"
repeatedly failed
to beat the placebo.
The promised
DHEA fountain of youth
was drying up.
A review of about two dozen
randomized controlled trials
of oral DHEA
in postmenopausal women
failed to find evidence
of improvements
in sexual function,
psychological well-being,
or cognitive performance.
However, there may be a role
for intravaginal DHEA
for vaginal atrophy,
which I covered before.
A meta-analysis
of about two dozen
randomized controlled trials
of DHEA in elderly men
similarly found no evidence
of benefits for metabolism,
bone health, sexual function,
or quality of life,
nor does there seem to be
a cognitive benefit.
The only benefit found in men
was a relatively trivial drop
in body fat compared to placebo,
less than one pound over a span
of eight months.
But in women,
DHEA may benefit fertility.
Fertility in women
starts declining gradually
but significantly at age 32,
but then more rapidly
after age 37,
but DHEA may help.
Side-effects
of taking DHEA supplements
include acne,
oily skin and hair,
and an increase in body hair
and blood levels
of the cancer-promoting
growth hormone IGF-1.
As with any supplement,
there are concerns
about quality control issues.
Some so-called
"DHEA" supplements
just blatantly lie
and have no DHEA whatsoever,
or up to, like,
150 percent of the listed dose.
For these and other reasons,
DHEA supplements
are not recommended.
Are there natural ways
to boost DHEA,
for example,
for the fertility benefit?
Lower protein intake is
associated with higher levels,
and an interventional trial
found increasing fiber intake
actively raised levels,
so what about
putting them together?
Enter: "Short-Term Impact
of a Lactovegetarian Diet."
After just five days
on an egg-free vegetarian diet,
blood levels
of the DHEA precursor rose
nearly 20 percent.
Or you can do it the other way:
Take those already eating
a plant-based diet
and switch them
to a conventional diet,
and their DHEA drops
up to nearly 20 percent.
The bodies of those
eating plant-based
appear to hold onto
the hormone better,
less urinary excretion,
which is normally something
you only see in fasting.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.